A Guide to the Correspondence and Subject Files of the Virgnia Secretary of Administration, 1972 - 1985 (Bulk 1984-1985)
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Correspondence and Subject Files of the Virgnia Secretary of Administration, 1972-1985
The Library of Virginia
32722
22 cu. ft. (22 boxes)
Virginia. Office of the Virginia Secretary of Administration
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Accession 32722 was transfered from the Office of the Virginia Secretary of Administration, on 13 May 1986, to the Virginia State Library and Archives for permanent retention.
Biographical Information
The Office of Administration was established in 1966 as part of the Office of the Governor to assist the chief executive in carrying out his duties. Several agencies including the divisions of the Budget, Personnel, Engineering and Building and Planning reported to the Commissioner of Administration. This system was inadequate. In 1970, the Governor's Management Commission Study recommended the creation of six "Deputy Governors" to assist the Chief Executive in his managerial duties. Compatible functions of government were grouped under these administrative heads, who would serve as the Governors top management team or "secretariats," as they are called now.
Governor Linwood Holton's top priority for the 1972 session of the General Assembly was a proposal for a Governor's Cabinet, reorganizing state agencies into six major departments--each headed by a secretary appointed by the governor. The Office of Administration was made one of these six departments. The office of Secretary of Administration was created on April 8, 1972, by an act passed by the General Assembly. Governor Holton appointed T. Edward Temple, the Commissioner of Administration since 1970, as the first Secretary of Administration. When Temple took office on July 1, 1972, he was responsible for the divisions of the Budget, Personnel, Engineering and Buildings, Automated Data Processing, Justice and Crime Prevention, State Planning and Community Affairs, Council on the Environment, State Board of Elections and the Office of Special Programs. The Office has undergone a series of administrative reorganizations since 1972. On April 12, 1976, the Legislature combined the secretariats for administration and finance, effective July 1, 1976. On July 1, 1984, the offices were separated. The Secretary of Administration is a member of the Governor's Cabinet, and is appointed by the governor, subject to confirmation by the General Assembly. Currently, the Secretary of Administration is responsible for the direction or jurisdiction over the following state agencies and boards: Department of Charitable Gaming, Compensation Board, State Board of Elections, Department of Employment Dispute Resolution, Department of General Services, Department of Human Resource Management, Council on Human Rights, Public Broadcasting Board, and the Department of Veterans Services.
T. Edward Temple, the first Secretary of Administration, announced in August 1973 that he was leaving state service effective January 1974. In December 1973, Governor-elect Mills E. Godwin, Jr., announced the appointment of Maurice B. Rowe, III, as Secretary of Administration. Rowe had served as Secretary of Commerce and Resources in the Holton administration. On July 1, 1976, the secretariates of administration and finance were combined. Rowe served until the end of the Godwin administration in January 1978 when he became Secretary of Commerce and Resources in the Dalton administration. In December 1977 Governor-elect John N. Dalton picked Charles B. Walker, the state comptroller, as Secretary of Administration and Finance. The office wielded great influence and authority under Walker who was known as the "Little Governor". Walker resigned in June 1981 to become a vice-president for Ethyl Corporation. Stuart Connock, state budget and planning director, served as Secretary of Administration and Finance until the end of Dalton's term in January 1982.
Governor-elect Charles S. Robb, the first Democrat to be elected governor since 1965, did not retain any of Dalton's cabinet secretaries. Robb appointed Wayne F. Anderson, a former Alexandria city manager, Secretary of Administration and Finance. Anderson announced his resignation in May 1984 to join the faculty of George Mason University. His resignation was prompted by a cabinet reorganization to take effect on July 1, 1984 which divided the Secretary of Administration and Finance into separate secretariats and combined the secretariats of transportation and public safety. Governor Robb appointed Secretary of Transportation Andrew B. Fogarty as new Secretary of Administration. Fogarty served until June 1985 when he became Sectretary of Transportation and Public Safety following the resignation of Franklin E. White. David K. McCloud, Robb's chief of staff, assumed the duties of Secretary of Administration for the remainder of Robb's term.
In December 1985, Governor-elect Gerald L. Baliles chose Carolyn J. Moss, head of the Office of Minority Business Enterprise under Governor Robb, as Secretary of Administration. Moss served until the end of Baliles' term in 1990. Governor-elect L. Douglas Wilder appointed Ruby G. Martin, a Richmond attorney, as Secretary of Administration. In January 1994 Governor-elect George Allen, the first Republican elected governor since 1977, appointed his campaign manager, Michael E. Thomas, Secretary of Administration. Thomas served until the end of Allen's term in January 1998. Governor James S. Gilmore appointed Thomas Deputy Secretary of Technology in August 1998. In January 1998 Governor-elect James S. Gilmore III named G. Bryan Slater as Secretary of Administration. Slater also served as Gilmore's Deputy Chief of Staff. He worked on Gilmore's campaign for attorney general in 1993 and served as his director of administration when Gilmore was Virginia Attorney General (1994-1997). Slater resigned in March 2001 to work for the Republican National Committee which Gilmore chaired. He was replaced by his deputy, Donald L. Moseley who served until the end of the Gilmore administration in January 2002.
Governor-elect Mark R. Warner selected Sandra Bowen as Secretary of Administration in January 2002. Bowen had previously served as Special Assistant to Governor Charles S. Robb, and as Secretary of the Commonwealth during the administration of Governor Gerald L. Baliles. She was also the Director of Gubernatorial Transition between the Robb and Baliles administrations. Secretary Bowen served under Governor Warner for his entire term, and was replaced in 2006 when Governor-elect Timothy Kaine selected Viola Baskerville as his Secretary of Administration.
Scope and Content
This series contains the correspondence and subject files from the Office of the Secretary of Administration, files fall into the catagories of Secretary of Administration, Executive Agreements, Board of Elections, Department of General Services, Department of Information Technology, Department of Personnel and Training, Virginia Supplimental Retirement System, Governor's Office, and Governor's Cabinet. Secretaries of Administration during this period were: T. Edward Temple, Maurice B. Rowe, Charles B. Walker, Stuart W. Connock, Wayne F. Anderson, and Dr. Andrew Fogarty.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
Series I. Correspondence and Subject Files
Contents List
- Series I. Correspondence and Subject Files, 1972-1985., Extent: 23 cu. ft. (23 boxes). (Box 1-23)
  This collection maintains the order assigned by the agency, which is catagorical and alphabetical.
  - Secretary of Administration: General, 1972-1985. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Secretary of Administration: Coke Bottling Contract, 1972-1985. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Secretary of Administration, 1972-1985. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Secretary of Administration: Directives, 1972-1985. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Secretary of Administration: Directives/ Temporary, 1972-1985. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Secretary of Administration: Employment Levels, 1972-1985. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Secretary of Administration: Financial Information/ General, 1972-1985. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Secretary of Administration: Governor's Fellow Project, 1985. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Secretary of Administration: General Correspondence (A-L), 1972-1985. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Secretary of Administration: General Correspondence (M-Z), 1972-1985. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Secretary of Administration: General Correspondence (Susan Urofsky), 1972-1985. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Secretary of Administration: Insurance, 1972-1985. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Secretary of Administration: David McCloud - Legislative Proposal, 1972-1985. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Secretary of Administration: Memoranda to Agencies and Institutions, 1972-1985. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Secretary of Administration: Personnel, Fritz, 1972-1985. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Secretary of Administration: Personnel, Temporary Employees, 1972-1985. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Secretary of Administration: Procedures - General, 1972-1985. (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Secretary of Administration: Staff, 1972-1985. (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Secretary of Administration: Surplus Property Report, 1972-1985. (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Secretary of Administration: Transition Memoranda, 1984 July. (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Secretary of Administration: Susan Urofsky - Speeches, 1972-1985. (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Secretary of Administration: Applications to Andrew Fogarty, 1972-1985. (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Executive Agreements: Compensation Board, 1972-1985. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Executive Agreements: State Board of Elections, 1972-1985. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Executive Agreements: Department of Information Technology, 1972-1985. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Executive Agreements: Office of Employee Relations Conselors, 1972-1985. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Executive Agreements: Secretary of the Commonwealth, 1972-1985. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Executive Agreements: Department of General Services, 1972-1985. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Executive Agreements: Liaison Office, 1972-1985. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Executive Agreements: Commission on Local Government, 1972-1985. (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Executive Agreements: Department of Personnel and Training, 1972-1985. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Executive Agreements: Virginia Supplimental Retirement System, 1972-1985. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Compensation Board: General, 1972-1985. (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - State Board of Elections: General, 1972-1985. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - State Board of Elections: Briefing Papers, 1984 July. (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - State Board of Elections: Commission to Increase Voter Registration, 1972-1985. (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Employee Relations Coucelors: General, 1972-1985. (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Employee Relations Coucelors: Briefing Papers, 1984 July. (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Employee Relations Coucelors: Study on Equal Employment Opportunity, 1972-1985. (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Employee Relations Coucelors: Grievance (SJR 38), 1984. (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Department of General Services: General, 1972-1985. (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Department of General Services: Consolidated Laboratories, 1972-1985. (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Department of General Services: Engineering and Building - Directives, 1972-1985. (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Department of General Services: Fiscals Services Support to Cabinet, 1972-1985. (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Department of General Services: Leasing Procedures, 1972-1985. (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Department of General Services: Maintenance of Public Facilities/Study, 1972-1985. (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Department of General Services: Office Space Needs Study - Downtown, 1972-1985. (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Department of General Services: Parking Study, 1972-1985. (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Department of General Services: Power Company Agreements, 1972-1985. (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Department of General Services: Prevent Maintenance, 1972-1985. (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Department of General Services: Print Shop Evaluation/Agency Printing Operations, 1972-1985. (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Department of General Services: Property/State Owned-Surplus, 1972-1985. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Department of General Services: Public Procurement Act, 1972-1985. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Department of General Services: Division of Purchases and Supply, 1972-1985. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Department of General Services: Office of Risk Management, 1972-1985. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Department of General Services: Secretarial Briefing Paper, 1984 July. (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Department of General Services: Section 11-55 - Code, 1972-1985. (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Department of General Services: Street Car Proposal - Science Musuem, 1972-1985. (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Department of General Services: Use of Legal-Size Paper, 1972-1985. (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Department of General Services: Virginia Business Opportunities Publication, 1972-1985. (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Hazard Waste Facility Sitting Board, 1972-1985. (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Department of Information Technology: General, 1972-1985. (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Department of Information Technology: Briefing, 1984 May 18. (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Department of Information Technology: ADP Procurement, 1972-1985. (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Department of Information Technology: Audits/Financial, 1972-1985. (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Department of Information Technology: Applications for Director, 1972-1985. (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Department of Information Technology: Graduate Televised Engineer Program, 1972-1985. (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Department of Information Technology: Organization Planning Documents, 1972-1985. (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Department of Information Technology: Procurement and Contracting Policies, 1972-1985. (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Department of Information Technology: Telecommunications Board, 1972-1985. (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Department of Information Technology: Telecommunications Division, 1972-1985. (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Department of Information Technology: Department of Information Technology Task Force, 1984. (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Virginia Liaison Office: Local Government, Commission of - General, 1972-1985. (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Virginia Liaison Office: Commission Members, 1972-1985. (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Department of Personnel and Training: Affirmative Action, 1972-1985. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Department of Personnel and Training: Audits/Financial, 1972-1985. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Department of Personnel and Training: Briefing on Secretary of Administration, 1984 July. (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Department of Personnel and Training: Transition Paper, 1984 Oct. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Department of Personnel and Training: Employee Complaints, 1972-1985. (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Department of Personnel and Training: Comparable Worth, 1972-1985. (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Department of Personnel and Training: Compensation Plan, Effective, 1972-1985. (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Department of Personnel and Training: General, 1972-1985. (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Department of Personnel and Training: Virginia Equal Employment Opportunity Council, 1972-1985. (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Department of Personnel and Training: Fair Labor Standards Act, 1972-1985. (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Department of Personnel and Training: Financial Proposals, 1986-88. (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Department of Personnel and Training: Hiring Trends, 1972-1985. (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Department of Personnel and Training: Holiday Schedules, 1972-1985. (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Department of Personnel and Training: Layoff Policy, 1972-1985. (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Department of Personnel and Training: Memoranda to Agency Heads and Personnel Officers, 1972-1985. (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Department of Personnel and Training: Missing Opportunity Report, 1972-1985. (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Department of Personnel and Training: Personnel, Bouchard, 1972-1985. (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Department of Personnel and Training: Recruit Program, 1972-1985. (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Department of Personnel and Training: Salary Srvey, 1983. (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Department of Personnel and Training: State Police Differentials, 1972-1985. (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Department of Personnel and Training: Time/Income Trade-Off Program, 1972-1985. (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Department of Personnel and Training: State Employee Assistance Service, 1972-1985. (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Department of Personnel and Training: Statewide Personnel Advisory Council, 1972-1985. (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Department of Personnel and Training: Work Hour Policies/Flex Time, 1972-1985. (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Department of Personnel and Training: Pay for Performance Compensation, 1972-1985. (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Department of Personnel and Training: Standards of Conduct and Performance, 1972-1985. (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Department of Personnel and Training: State Grievance Procedure, 1972-1985. (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Department of Personnel and Training: Suggestion Awards Program, 1972-1985. (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Department of Personnel and Training: DPT Status, 1972-1985. (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Department of Personnel and Training: Comments on Draft Manual, 1972-1985. (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Department of Personnel and Training: New Jersey Administrative Code, 1972-1985. (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Department of Personnel and Training: Profiles of Others States, 1972-1985. (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Department of Personnel and Training: SAP Manual - Minnesota, Alabama, Washington, 1972-1985. (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Department of Personnel and Training: SAP - Missouri, 1972-1985. (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Department of Personnel and Training: North Carolina Promotion Manuals, 1972-1985. (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Department of Personnel and Training: Virginia - Draft Manuals, 1972-1985. (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Department of Personnel and Training: Concept Paper, 1972-1985. (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Department of Personnel and Training: Manual Drafts, 1972-1985. (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Department of Personnel and Training: Legal Issues, 1972-1985. (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Department of Personnel and Training: Background Paper, 1972-1985. (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Department of Personnel and Training: Florida - Manuals, Forms, Promotion, 1972-1985. (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Virginia Supplemental Retirement System: General, 1972-1985. (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Virginia Supplemental Retirement System: Disability Program, 1972-1985. (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Virginia Supplemental Retirement System: Deferred Compensation, 1972-1985. (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Virginia Supplemental Retirement System: Financial/Audits/DBP, 1972-1985. (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Virginia Supplemental Retirement System: Descriptive, 1972-1985. (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Governor's Office: Robb Administration Agency Head Resumes, 1972-1985. (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Governor's Office: Agency Head Appointments/Robb, 1972-1985. (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Governor's Office: Robb Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1972-1985. (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Governor's Office: General Correspondence A-F, 1972-1985. (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Governor's Office: General Correspondence G-L, 1972-1985. (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Governor's Office: General Correspondence M-R, 1972-1985. (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Governor's Office: General Correspondence S-Z, 1972-1985. (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Governor's Office: Guidance Packages, 1982-1984. (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Governor's Office: Limousine Purchase, 1972-1985. (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Governor's Office: Directives, 1972-1985. (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Governor's Office: Mansion, 1972-1985. (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Governor's Office: Transition/Robb, 1982-1984. (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Governor's Office: Policy Memoranda, 1982-1984. (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Governor's Cabinet: Candidates for Secretaries, 1982-1984. (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Governor's Cabinet: Administration and Finance, 1982-1984. (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Governor's Cabinet: Commerce and Resources, 1982-1984. (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Governor's Cabinet: Secretary of the Commonwealth, 1982-1984. (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Governor's Cabinet: Education, 1982-1984. (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Governor's Cabinet: Finance, 1982-1984. (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Governor's Cabinet: Human Resources, 1982-1984. (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Governor's Cabinet: Public Safety, 1982-1984. (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Governor's Cabinet: Transportation, 1982-1984. (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Governor's Cabinet by Subject: Cabinet Salaries, 1982-1984. (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Governor's Cabinet by Subject: Forums and Congressional Meetings, 1982-1984. (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Governor's Cabinet by Subject: General, 1982-1984. (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Governor's Cabinet by Subject: Organizational Staffing, 1982-1984. (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Governor's Cabinet by Subject: Relocation to the Sixth Floor, 1982-1984. (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Governor's Cabinet by Subject: Retreat - Camp Pendleton, 1982-1984. (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Governor's Cabinet by Subject: Retreats, 1982-1984. (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Governor's Cabinet by Subject: Staff Salaries and Leave Balances, 1982-1984. (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Governor's Cabinet by Subject: Work Sessions, 1982-1984. (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Teachers Insurance and Annuity Association/College Retirement Equities Fund, 1982-1984. (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Teachers Insurance and Annuity Association/College Retirement Equities Fund - Working Papers, 1982-1984. (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Teachers Insurance and Annuity Association/College Retirement Equities Fund - Process Meetings, 1982-1984. (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Teachers Insurance and Annuity Association/College Retirement Equities Fund - Briefing paper, 1982-1984. (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Teachers Insurance and Annuity Association/College Retirement Equities Fund - Legal Problems, 1982-1984. (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Teachers Insurance and Annuity Association/College Retirement Equities Fund - Policy Cost, 1982-1984. (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Teachers Insurance and Annuity Association/College Retirement Equities Fund - Draft Guidelines, 1982-1984. (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Teachers Insurance and Annuity Association/College Retirement Equities Fund - Background to Issue, 1982-1984. (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Teachers Insurance and Annuity Association/College Retirement Equities Fund - Commpensation Guidelines, 1982-1984. (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Teachers Insurance and Annuity Association/College Retirement Equities Fund - Comparative, 1982-1984. (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Teachers Insurance and Annuity Association/College Retirement Equities Fund - Descriptive, 1982-1984. (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Realignment, Reevaluation, etc.: Reorganization - General, 1982-1984. (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Realignment, Reevaluation, etc.: Critical Reevaluation - Process/Meetings, 1982-1984. (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Realignment, Reevaluation, etc.: Critical Reevaluation - Policy Papers, 1982-1984. (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - Realignment, Reevaluation, etc.: Critical Reevaluation - Governor's Speeches, 1982-1984. (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - Realignment, Reevaluation, etc.: Critical Reevaluation - Miscellaneous, 1982-1984. (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Realignment, Reevaluation, etc.: Critical Reevaluation - Conference, 1983 Sept. (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Realignment, Reevaluation, etc.: Critical Reevaluation, 1983 July-Dec. (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Realignment, Reevaluation, etc.: Critical Reevaluation, 1982-1983 June. (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Realignment, Reevaluation, etc.: Realignment, 1984. (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Comparable Worth: Federal Materials, 1982-1984. (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - House Document 5 - Commission of Status of Women: Research Materials, 1982-1984. (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - House Document 5 - Commission of Status of Women: Mail Requests, 1982-1984. (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - House Document 5 - Commission of Status of Women: Mobility Legislation, 1982-1984. (Box 9, Folder 4)